<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Core Dumps</title><link href="https://aufarg.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://aufarg.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://aufarg.github.io/</id><updated>2017-02-03T01:48:49+07:00</updated><entry><title>BTRFS: Access Beyond End of Device</title><link href="https://aufarg.github.io/btrfs-access-beyond-end-of-device.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-03T01:48:49+07:00</published><updated>2017-02-03T01:48:49+07:00</updated><author><name>aufarg</name></author><id>tag:aufarg.github.io,2017-02-03:/btrfs-access-beyond-end-of-device.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: There's a problem in my filesystem and it made my important
file corrupted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;em&gt;What's the scariest thing that happened in your life?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I want to share one of the scariest thing that happened to me:
BTRFS filesystem suddenly attempt to access beyond end of device …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: There's a problem in my filesystem and it made my important
file corrupted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;em&gt;What's the scariest thing that happened in your life?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I want to share one of the scariest thing that happened to me:
BTRFS filesystem suddenly attempt to access beyond end of device and somehow it
made my GnuPG keyring into junk. GnuPG keyring is the one file that contains
key for public-key cryptography. Attempting to access beyond the end of device
made BTRFS auto-remount the device into read-only. And it happened right when
I'm playing with my gpg keyring (which I used to encrypt some important
passwords).  By the time I realized the problem, the keyfile has become junk in
the said device. Right now, I already solved the problem with some methods
which luckily available to me. Since I don't want the same experience haunts
other people, here's the full story of what happened and what I did to fix it.
I hope you'll find it useful!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, in a rainy day, I was inspecting my gpg keyring. I just
wanted to see what kind of file it is in binary. I kind of like randomly
seeing binary files (I know it's weird) to waste time. It's a great joy
looking at those unreadable, otherworldly junk text until when I quit (with
:wq for save-then-quit), vim gave me warning that it cannot sync with the
filesystem. Wait what? I wasn't even changing the file so what could
happened? Luckily the file buffer on vim is not closed yet (nice error
handling vim devs!), and I could copy the entire content of my keyring to
clipboard. But, where should I put it now? I tried saving into some other
file in my home folder and it gave the same error. Apparently, I tried to
create some random with contents and it failed (horribly so!). So I recall
that these kind of weird errors usually born from some kernel component and
look what I've got in my system log:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Feb 01 03:08:01 Tyria kernel: BTRFS error (device dm-1): bdev
/dev/mapper/Arch-home errs: wr 1, rd 0, flush 0, corrupt 0, gen 0
Feb 01 03:08:01 Tyria kernel: attempt to access beyond end of device
Feb 01 03:08:01 Tyria kernel: dm-1: rw=536871000, want=329009280,
limit=329007104
Feb 01 03:08:01 Tyria kernel: BTRFS error (device dm-1): bdev
/dev/mapper/Arch-home errs: wr 2, rd 0, flush 0, corrupt 0, gen 0
Feb 01 03:08:01 Tyria kernel: BTRFS: error (device dm-1) in
btrfs_commit_transaction:2227: errno=-5 IO failure (Error while writing
out transaction)
Feb 01 03:08:01 Tyria kernel: BTRFS info (device dm-1): forced readonly
Feb 01 03:08:01 Tyria kernel: BTRFS warning (device dm-1): Skipping commit
of aborted transaction.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I &lt;strong&gt;DO&lt;/strong&gt; know that BTRFS is still experimental, and I kind of embraced the
errors that may come to me. But... I didn't expect the kind of error where
the filesystem tried to access beyond bounds.  Ok, what happened is
happened, but for now I need to somehow save my keyring first. Looking at
the error message I kind of guess it just happened on my /dev/Arch/home
device, so I might try saving it on /dev/Arch/root and voila! It works! Good
now I can go on to diagnose and fixing my filesystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Diagnosing &amp;amp; Fixing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, the first time I read the error, I don't even understand why it
attempt to access something beyond the end of device. It doesn't even make
sense, and I thought it tried to allocate new blocks somewhere outside the
device (which still doesn't make sense, because if the filesystem is full it
should give an error instead of attempting to write). I don't know what
caused BTRFS to act like that and just plain search it on the web which
solutions varies and after reading the problems again, they're differ too.
Apparently, this error message is given by the kernel for various filesystem
problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since there's no specific problem related to the error message, I just tried
the basic &lt;code&gt;btrfs scrub start &amp;lt;path&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to find some leads. Scrubbing works by
checking device's blocks and metadata checksum and then compare it with the
one in the filesystem table, you got some errors if it differs. So, if
there's something wrong I should be able to notice.  But then it was aborted
in, like, 5 seconds right after I run it and only scrubbed 54 &lt;strong&gt;MiB&lt;/strong&gt; of
space. Of course my filesystem is waaay more than that. And scrubbing also
gives new but same errors as before. So I guess what happened is when it's
trying to scrub, there's some file that is out of bound and boom, there goes
the errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now, how do I access them then? Luckily, I've got a nice logical volume
(LV) layout like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;start ---------------------------------------- end
      |    root    |    home    |    swap    |
                          ^
                     problematic
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thus, my plan is remove the &lt;code&gt;swap&lt;/code&gt; LV, extend the &lt;code&gt;home&lt;/code&gt; LV, somehow gather
all the files' bits into the start of the LV, then shrink the &lt;code&gt;home&lt;/code&gt; back,
and recreate the swap. Okay, here we go! First of all, remove the &lt;code&gt;swap&lt;/code&gt; LV
and extend the &lt;code&gt;home&lt;/code&gt; LV:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;# swapoff /dev/swap
# lvremove /dev/swap
# lvextend -l +100%FREE /dev/home
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And the layout become like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;start ---------------------------------------- end
      |    root    |           home          |
                                 ^
                            problematic
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After that, I use &lt;code&gt;btrfs scrub start /dev/home&lt;/code&gt; to see if everything is
fine. Since I'm not patient, I run &lt;code&gt;watch btrfs scrub status /dev/home&lt;/code&gt; so I
can monitor it. 10 Gigs, 30 Gigs, 50 Gigs, ..., and some minutes later it's
done! Nice, so the files are really goes beyond the end &lt;code&gt;/dev/home&lt;/code&gt; LV and
we can try to gather the files. How do we do that? Fortunately, BTRFS
provides an on-line defragment tool with &lt;code&gt;btrfs filesystem defragment
&amp;lt;partition&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. At this point, I'm not really sure how BTRFS defragment works.
Usually it works like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="defragment illustration" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d0/FragmentationDefragmentation.gif" title="Defragment Illustration"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's usually implementation dependent, but nothing to lose right? (unless
the defragment feature is still experimental and I'll lose all my date
T_T). So I ran &lt;code&gt;btrfs filesystem defragment /dev/home&lt;/code&gt;, and then wait till
it's done. How to check if it DOES worked? I don't know. Let's just try
return the LVs like before and then run BTRFS scrub:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;# lvresize -L &amp;lt;previous /dev/home size&amp;gt; /dev/home
# lvcreate -L &amp;lt;previous /dev/swap size&amp;gt; -n swap &amp;lt;group name&amp;gt;
# mkswap /dev/swap
# swapon /dev/swap
# btrfs scrub start /dev/home
# watch btrfs scrub status /dev/home
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After a moment, it says all the filesystem is checked and no errors on
systemd-journald and I can write things again. Yay! It does worked afterall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sure is scary when my keyring almost gone, but it's
fun trying to fix the problem (although I don't know if this is truly a fix
or not). With that said, I think I can fix this because I'm lucky that right
after my &lt;code&gt;/dev/home&lt;/code&gt; LV is my swap LV so I can remove it. I wonder what
should I do if it's not a swap LV (like, if the &lt;code&gt;/dev/root&lt;/code&gt; trying to access
&lt;code&gt;/dev/home&lt;/code&gt;)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two things that I learn from this incident:
- Don't straight restart your machine if something failed on your computer.
  Make sure you don't have any loss first before going for the
  restart-route. Besides your own data, save the error logs that you got for
  future diagnose purpose (in case the error is not saved). You can always use
  pen and paper if you can't save it digitally.
- Actually, try not to use the restart-route if possible, especially if you
  use the computer quite often. It's just running from the problem.
  Restart-route will solve transient problems, and most likely it will
  happened again. Of course I can say this because I got the basic idea of
  how it works, but then again, you should have a friend (you do right?)
  that understand what happened. You're not living alone.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Implementation vs Design</title><link href="https://aufarg.github.io/implementation-vs-design.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-18T02:30:24+07:00</published><updated>2017-01-18T02:30:24+07:00</updated><author><name>aufarg</name></author><id>tag:aufarg.github.io,2017-01-18:/implementation-vs-design.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my school, there's a common dogma that software implementation is easy,
the hard part is designing. This dogma emerge as I take software engineering
classes. The lecturers keep a big emphasize on how cool to design a software
and how lame to implement a software. For me, I always …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my school, there's a common dogma that software implementation is easy,
the hard part is designing. This dogma emerge as I take software engineering
classes. The lecturers keep a big emphasize on how cool to design a software
and how lame to implement a software. For me, I always confused about that
dogma. Mostly because I don't know which processes are design and which are
implementation. But I asked my friends and they're confused too. So, I discuss
with my friends and came up with these thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The definition given to me is implementation is a process to realized the
design and it's actually only the "coding" part. "Coding" here means to write
the code, that's it. But it doesn't make sense since the person who do the
design and the implementation is different. That means if the one who
implements only write the code, the design specification should consists of
detailed algorithm (that is, describe the program action by action) in another
language (most likely natural language or pseudocode).  It's weird because why
would the designer write the code in some language just to be rewritten again
in some programming language?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, maybe the language that's being used to create the design document is
easier to learn and "easier" to understand. But it's still inefficient
because no matter what language you write it with, the "coder" WILL ask you
about some part of the design (that is, the meaning particular sequence of
action) because you can't always translate an action between the design
document language and the programming language and the "coder" will need to
make sure that they have understand what you mean. This kind of
communication will slow down the development process and it's not efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One argument is that since the "coder" will have lower salary than the
designer (since "coding" is easier"), we can lower the budget too. Well, if
the design document is written action by action, the rate that design
document created will be the same as (if not longer than) the
implementation (designing requires thinking, "coding" can take a look at
reference). Unless we want the implementation be stuck waiting on the
design, we need to have many designer too so, no, we actually need more
budget (and still inefficient too).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess I just misheard my lecturers and that's not what they meant. So I'll
just the one in
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_implementation"&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;: software
implementation (as a verb) is "the process of computer programming". The
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_programming"&gt;computer programming&lt;/a&gt;
page defines programming as "activities such as analysis, developing
understanding, generating algorithms, verification of requirements of
algorithms including their correctness and resources consumption, and
implementation (commonly referred to as coding) of algorithms in a target
programming language".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, "coding" is part of implementation. But implementation includes so much
more than that. The person who do the implementation (let's call them the
programmer) will need to understand how the program will work. In fact,
according to the definition, the programmer's understanding of the language
also determines the correctness of the implementation. I think it's
also important to get the correctness of the implementation, not just the
correctness on the concept. Also, while concept is nice, sometimes
understanding of implementations can let you create a more practical concept
(even though messier) than the neat concept. This is the case (or at least
similar) with OSI vs IP described in &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/166190.Computer_Networks"&gt;Computer
Networks&lt;/a&gt; by
Andrew Tanembaum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I'm trying to say here is that software implementation does not
necessarily easier than software design, it may deal with something
deterministic and the answer is already there, but you still need to KNOW
the knowledge to do that. It may not require as much as creativity as
software designing, but hey, you won't say being a doctor is easy right?
(and if doctor use their creativity on their job, I'll be shit scared)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But maybe it's just me that is too stupid to understand what my lecturers mean.
It's just, I'm sad that my school teaching me to lookdown on someone's job,
regardless if it's easier or not. I always think it's best to respect any
job and don't compare which is harder/cooler/profitable-r/yadayada, as
long as the job is doing something good to humanity.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>