<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>aufarg:/var/log $ _ - journal</title><link href="https://aufarg.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://aufarg.github.io/feeds/journal.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://aufarg.github.io/</id><updated>2017-11-29T22:02:52+07:00</updated><entry><title>Capture The Fun: Cyber Sea Game 2017</title><link href="https://aufarg.github.io/capture-the-fun-cyber-sea-game-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-29T12:00:49+07:00</published><updated>2017-11-29T22:02:52+07:00</updated><author><name>Aufar Gilbran</name></author><id>tag:aufarg.github.io,2017-11-29:/capture-the-fun-cyber-sea-game-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;After Cyber Jawara&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me and my &lt;a href="https://ctftime.org/team/16919"&gt;team&lt;/a&gt; are fortunate enough to be selected to
represent Indonesia in Cyber Sea Game 2017 as part of the 1st place prize. It's a CTF event held
by partnership between Japan and ASEAN countries (I think, I'm not sure). The winner of the
event …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;After Cyber Jawara&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me and my &lt;a href="https://ctftime.org/team/16919"&gt;team&lt;/a&gt; are fortunate enough to be selected to
represent Indonesia in Cyber Sea Game 2017 as part of the 1st place prize. It's a CTF event held
by partnership between Japan and ASEAN countries (I think, I'm not sure). The winner of the
event will be sent to &lt;a href="https://2017.seccon.jp"&gt;SECCON 2017&lt;/a&gt; as guest team. To be honest, the
competition is a bit shady to me. There's no official website nor place to get information and
the prize is too good to be true (it's very hard to pass SECCON quals). We only know that the
event will be held in Thailand from Indonesian officials. As a good guy, I believe what the
official said to me and practice for the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Call me skeptical, but I really thought that we will not win. Part of it because my teammates,
V, says that Singapore and Vietnam team are pretty strong. Since he's our best member, I'm
scared af to the point that I thought I'll just practice to make sure I'm not regretting it
later without thinking the possibilities of winning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Preparing for Cyber Sea Game 2017&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I was recently graduated, I had a ton of time to practice. But, even after graduating, I'm
none of the wiser. Instead, I put half of my time playing some MMO game. Well, it's still half a
ton of time to practice. Neato! I wasn't sure to ask my other teammates to practice together
because I'm so bad and I'm afraid the intelligence among us is distributed (i.e. they become
more stupid) because of me. So instead, I did what the loners do when they do things.
Practicing alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've always liked cryptography (mathematically, not technically) and binary exploitation. So
that's what I practiced most of the time. Cryptography is quite hard to practice because usually
cryptography exploitation in CTF events involves edge cases in the formula or has some gimmicky
usage. So I just read some cool ctf writeups for cryptography to get the sense of what a
cryptosystem could do, which part of the system are the weak links, etc. In constrat, binary
exploitation is easier to practice because there are many wargames to practice on. I decide to
just continue working through &lt;a href="http://pwnable.kr/"&gt;pwnable.kr&lt;/a&gt; challenges. The problems are
unique for their own category so I won't be too familiar with the techniques, but it also means
I could catch up (in term of knowledge) my teammate which specialize in binary exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some days before the competition, suddenly there was an email from Japan side regarding
registered participants. It appeared that they don't accommodate coaches, but the maximum of
participants in a team is actually 4 persons. So after some short period of shocks, we need to
search one more member.  So we asked the only person that we know we
could-ask-to-fill-in-without-causing-too-much-drama. The problem-setter for Cyber Jawara. He
accepted. We filled in. Yay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, we went to Thailand (and skip to the contest right away)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Cyber Sea Game 2017&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contest was held in a meeting room (I think, I forgot) in Swissôtel Le Concorde. They
created a local network platform which requires you to connect through an ethernet cable they
provided and you can use Wi-Fi to browse the internet. I wonder why they limit local connection
from the internet though. Maybe to prevent DOS? I'm not sure. They gave us time to setup the
network and see if we had any problem, which unfortunately I had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned that my &lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/netctl"&gt;network manager&lt;/a&gt; by default
don't let me use both ethernet and Wi-Fi. I think there's a way to do it but I got no time so I
just disconnect the ethernet when I want to browse the internet and connect to the ethernet when
I want to submit flag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, the contest begin. They give some problems. I don't remember the others, but they only
give 2 crypto problems with 200 and 250 points, and 1 pwn problems with 300 points. Of course
they'll give high point pwn problems first. So I decide to tackle the lowest crypto problems
first. Seems like lady luck still hates me even after the network problem, and now I got a
technical crypto problem involving &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_key_certificate"&gt;digital
certificate&lt;/a&gt;. Great. V solved a reverse
engineering problem which give us 50 points. But then, Vietnam team got 160~ points. Cool. After
two hours, I only able to extract some garbage message (which I think will be decrypted by some
means) and extract the upper-level certificate. I don't actually understand what they do.
Meanwhile, the Thailand team that already solve it, which give them 250~ points. Fortunately, on
the brink of my despair, it was lunch time! After having so much fun munching tasty food, we go
back to contest site. The first two hour, with only 50 points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second part of the contest begin, and then they released many problems altogether. In total,
there were 30 problems available to solve. They actually released a &lt;a href="https://aufarg.github.io/cyber-sea-game-2017-addcrypto-50.html"&gt;50 point
crypto&lt;/a&gt;. An original cryptosystem. With
only math logic. Finally! That problem is actually my savior because it gives me the momentum
that I need to solve other challenges. After solving other crypto problems, my teammates start
to ask for help so we start working together on some weird challenges. One of the weird problems
is a binary data file with a picture showing the hexdump result of the binary. The problem name
is called md5, which is quite weird. We only realized that we need to take each line of the
hexdump as md5 hexes and look it up in md5 databases. Sadly, we recovered the flag about 10
seconds (!!!) after the contest is over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the moment of truth is, the winner annoucement. While we managed to rack good amount of
points, we were pretty nervous about the result as the scoreboard is frozen and we were on 3rd
place on last update. To make it worse, Singapore team, who were at 2nd place, also yelling
"Yesss" quite loudly near the end of the contest with a 400 point problem update to have 1 team
solve. That means they got 400 points + 80 bonus points. Sigh. My teammates already lose hope
because the only way for us to winning this is to have the other teams not getting too much
points and Singapore team not getting any other points beside the 400 points problem. I still
hoped to win because it's still probable point-wise. Maybe another miracle will happen to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it did happen. Again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We won by 20 points difference from Singapore team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Cyber Sea Game 2017 Scoreboard" src="https://aufarg.github.io/images/cyber-sea-game-2017-scoreboard.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of a sudden, all the weight from my shoulders disappeared and I see my teammates shocked
and smiling happily. We actually won our first international CTF event. Winning also make us the
guest team that will be sent to SECCON 2017. THE SECCON. After the event, we went to our room
and rest. The next day, we took the flight home while being proud of our achievement (well, at
least I did).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I'm very happy and thankful for my very skilled teammates, my friend (whom always
remind me to practice), and Indonesian officials that made all of this possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For (successfully recovered) writeups, you can find it &lt;a href="/tag/cyber-sea-game.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Some
problems that I solved are not here because either it wasn't purely my work or some of the
problem files cannot be found in my laptop.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="cyber-sea-game"></category><category term="ctf-story"></category></entry><entry><title>Capture The Fun: Cyber Jawara 2017</title><link href="https://aufarg.github.io/capture-the-fun-cyber-jawara-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-29T12:00:16+07:00</published><updated>2017-11-29T12:00:16+07:00</updated><author><name>Aufar Gilbran</name></author><id>tag:aufarg.github.io,2017-11-29:/capture-the-fun-cyber-jawara-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a long time urging to write a
(&lt;a href="https://aufarg.github.io/btrfs-access-beyond-end-of-device.html"&gt;not-so-random&lt;/a&gt;) story in my blog,
finally I had the time to actually write some things. For my debut on my own blog, the first
thing to write that comes to mind is my Capture the Flag (CTF) story. We start right when …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a long time urging to write a
(&lt;a href="https://aufarg.github.io/btrfs-access-beyond-end-of-device.html"&gt;not-so-random&lt;/a&gt;) story in my blog,
finally I had the time to actually write some things. For my debut on my own blog, the first
thing to write that comes to mind is my Capture the Flag (CTF) story. We start right when I'm
done with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Competitive_programming"&gt;competitive programming&lt;/a&gt; and
start focusing for CTF (and struggling to graduate from my university). Let's start with a bit
of introduction of my history in CTF events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me and my &lt;a href="https://ctftime.org/team/16919"&gt;team&lt;/a&gt; have had quite a long time of history in CTF
events. One of my friend, V, just happened to ask me to form a new CTF team with N (which is my
friend too). At the time, I'm still excited learning Linux because I just recently learned to
use it. I thought I can learn things about Linux there so why not? I accepted it and we form a
new CTF team. Neat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was hard for us to learn things because there was no established CTF team in my university.
Luckily for me, my two friend were pretty knowledgeable right off the bat. Apparently, V already
doing reverse engineering since middle/high-school and N has done system administrator thingies.
So I tried to learn things from them to catch up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't talk much about things that had happened around this time. Mainly because I was focused
more on doing competitive programming much more than CTF. But then I was also struggling to
graduate and I can't give too much focus on CTF. So it wasn't until my next CTF competition that
I learned I really need to catch up with people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Dawn Age&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point in July, my team participate in CTF event called Computer Festival. It was a
(supposed-to-be) nation-wide free-for-all CTF event. That means this event does not restrict
participants by maximum age nor academic status (I think there's still restriction for minimum
age). This is also the first event with my new temmate, J, which replace N.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was on this event that I realized things cannot stay like this if I want to go with these
people. I need to be able to contribute. At that time, my only merit is I can create
shell-script quite fast to automate exploitation, which is quite useful for attack and defense
style. But you can't get more points without the ability to exploit things. We ended up in 2nd
place for this event, mostly because V is very skilled. I know I should increase the intensity
for learning, especially because the winning team (let's call it Team US) have had beaten us
more than I could count for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1st through 3rd place of the event is invited to participate in Cyber Jawara, an annual
nation-wide CTF event. I decided that I will learn more about cryptography and binary
exploitation so I can contribute things there. With cryptography usually not included as on-site
problems, I should pump up my binary exploitation skill. Searching for resources to learn
binary exploitation, I tumbled upon &lt;a href="http://pwnable.kr"&gt;pwnable.kr&lt;/a&gt;. I spent my time until right
before Cyber Jawara by preparing my graduation and do some pwnable.kr problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, the day had come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cyber Jawara 2017&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contest were split into 2 phase. The first phase is reverse engineering and forensic, and
the second phase is web and binary exploitation. The first phase had 30% weight with
jeopardy-style so we only need to solve the problems given to us. The second
phase had 70% weight and we need to defend ourself from other team attacks by patching the
service. No cryptography, I knew it. So the only chance for me to contribute is binary
exploitation problems. I'm also quite lucky because the higher weight phase requires some
automation that I can contribute at the very least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first phase, no one in my team really understand forensic and their tools so we try to
rack points from reverse engineering. Apparently, one of the problem require us to solve
constraint satisfiability. This can be done with &lt;a href="https://github.com/Z3Prover/z3"&gt;Z3&lt;/a&gt;. But none
of us know how to use it. So we were behind in term of points at this phase. I think we were
behind by ~300 points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the second phase, V was racking up points from web problems. Me and J attempt the binary
exploitation problem. J attempted the 300 points pwn, while I just tried to lessen their burden
by doing 50 and 150 points pwn. The 50 points pwn is just a backdoor by putting some weird bytes
before the payload so it's quite easy. I still took my time though because I'm slow when it
comes to reading the application logic. I patched the binary by nop-ing the backdoor check then
moved on to 150 points pwn. The 150 points pwn is pwning a python service + shell.  Great, it's
NOT a BINARY exploitation. Well, at least I can solve it. It's kinda upsetting that the result
of me practicing hours at pwnable.kr won't be seen here but I'm quite happy to contribute. I
patched the 150 points pwn by making sure the python service is not pwnable and moved on to help
J with 300 points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, V start asked for my help with automation and finding exploitation. He ended up
finding them all by himself and I just help with the automation though. There was a weird 100
points web problem that perplexed me and V. Apparently, it use a framework which you can access
it's debugging console by going requesting &lt;code&gt;/console&lt;/code&gt;. Great, I missed reading the console part
when I'm looking through the framework source code. Meanwhile, J had solved the problem and he
needs a bit of time to patch it. We don't know if he'll made it in time. We were only winning
the second phase by 90 points. Yes, if we calculate it right, we're still behind in term of
total points (90x0.7 - 300x0.3). The good news is, J just finished patched the binary that he
solved 3 minutes near the end of the contest. V and J already hoped that at least we get the 2nd
place. I was still hoping for the X factor like binary-patching and writeups. Maybe there will
be a miracle...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it did happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We actually won the by measly amount of 50 or so points. Mind you, the total point is 3030
points so it's a pretty slim difference. I don't know what's the cause but I'm happy anyway. I
learned just how a small contribution could bring big impact to the table. We suspect that it's
because J had the time to patched it and we got more points for it. If J doesn't start doing the
300 points pwn right away, I'm pretty sure the result will be different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I'm a bit upset that my contribution is still low but at least I made an impact
there. At this point I had the momentum to keep learning for CTF events and will ride on it to
keep contributing. Still, it was great pleasure to finally beat Team US after all this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is made 2 months after the event so I didn't recall some minutiae like phase weights
and problem points. I try to write it as accurate as possible to make the reader aware what I
felt and why I felt that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wrote the writeups, but we haven't published it yet. Since it's a hassle to convert between
Google Docs and Markdown, I'm not gonna do it. If you want to read the writeup you can contact
me and maybe I can just dump the PDF version for you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="cyber-jawara"></category><category term="ctf-story"></category></entry><entry><title>BTRFS: Access Beyond End of Device</title><link href="https://aufarg.github.io/btrfs-access-beyond-end-of-device.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-10T02:29:43+07:00</published><updated>2017-11-28T17:06:25+07:00</updated><author><name>Aufar Gilbran</name></author><id>tag:aufarg.github.io,2017-02-10:/btrfs-access-beyond-end-of-device.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: There's a problem in my filesystem and it made my important
file corrupted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;em&gt;What's the scariest thing that happened in your life?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I want to share one of the scariest thing that happened to me:
BTRFS filesystem suddenly attempt to access beyond end of device …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: There's a problem in my filesystem and it made my important
file corrupted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;em&gt;What's the scariest thing that happened in your life?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I want to share one of the scariest thing that happened to me:
BTRFS filesystem suddenly attempt to access beyond end of device and somehow it
made my GnuPG keyring into junk. GnuPG keyring is the one file that contains
key for public-key cryptography. Attempting to access beyond the end of device
made BTRFS auto-remount the device into read-only. And it happened right when
I'm playing with my gpg keyring (which I used to encrypt some important
passwords).  By the time I realized the problem, the keyfile has become junk in
the said device. Right now, I already solved the problem with some methods
which luckily available to me. Since I don't want the same experience haunts
other people, here's the full story of what happened and what I did to fix it.
I hope you'll find it useful!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, in a rainy day, I was inspecting my gpg keyring. I just
wanted to see what kind of file it is in binary. I kind of like randomly
seeing binary files (I know it's weird) to waste time. It's a great joy
looking at those unreadable, otherworldly junk text until when I quit (with
:wq for save-then-quit), vim gave me warning that it cannot sync with the
filesystem. Wait what? I wasn't even changing the file so what could
happened? Luckily the file buffer on vim is not closed yet (nice error
handling vim devs!), and I could copy the entire content of my keyring to
clipboard. But, where should I put it now? I tried saving into some other
file in my home folder and it gave the same error. Apparently, I tried to
create some random with contents and it failed (horribly so!). So I recall
that these kind of weird errors usually born from some kernel component and
look what I've got in my system log:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Feb 01 03:08:01 Tyria kernel: BTRFS error (device dm-1): bdev&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;/dev/mapper/Arch-home errs: wr 1, rd 0, flush 0, corrupt 0, gen 0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;Feb 01 03:08:01 Tyria kernel: attempt to access beyond end of device&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;Feb 01 03:08:01 Tyria kernel: dm-1: rw=536871000, want=329009280,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;limit=329007104&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;Feb 01 03:08:01 Tyria kernel: BTRFS error (device dm-1): bdev&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;/dev/mapper/Arch-home errs: wr 2, rd 0, flush 0, corrupt 0, gen 0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;Feb 01 03:08:01 Tyria kernel: BTRFS: error (device dm-1) in&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;btrfs_commit_transaction:2227: errno=-5 IO failure (Error while writing&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;out transaction)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;Feb 01 03:08:01 Tyria kernel: BTRFS info (device dm-1): forced readonly&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;Feb 01 03:08:01 Tyria kernel: BTRFS warning (device dm-1): Skipping commit&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;of aborted transaction.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I &lt;strong&gt;DO&lt;/strong&gt; know that BTRFS is still experimental, and I kind of embraced the
errors that may come to me. But... I didn't expect the kind of error where
the filesystem tried to access beyond bounds.  Ok, what happened is
happened, but for now I need to somehow save my keyring first. Looking at
the error message I kind of guess it just happened on my /dev/Arch/home
device, so I might try saving it on /dev/Arch/root and voila! It works! Good
now I can go on to diagnose and fixing my filesystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Diagnosing &amp;amp; Fixing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, the first time I read the error, I don't even understand why it
attempt to access something beyond the end of device. It doesn't even make
sense, and I thought it tried to allocate new blocks somewhere outside the
device (which still doesn't make sense, because if the filesystem is full it
should give an error instead of attempting to write). I don't know what
caused BTRFS to act like that and just plain search it on the web which
solutions varies and after reading the problems again, they're differ too.
Apparently, this error message is given by the kernel for various filesystem
problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since there's no specific problem related to the error message, I just tried
the basic &lt;code&gt;btrfs scrub start &amp;lt;path&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to find some leads. Scrubbing works by
checking device's blocks and metadata checksum and then compare it with the
one in the filesystem table, you got some errors if it differs. So, if
there's something wrong I should be able to notice.  But then it was aborted
in, like, 5 seconds right after I run it and only scrubbed 54 &lt;strong&gt;MiB&lt;/strong&gt; of
space. Of course my filesystem is waaay more than that. And scrubbing also
gives new but same errors as before. So I guess what happened is when it's
trying to scrub, there's some file that is out of bound and boom, there goes
the errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now, how do I access them then? Luckily, I've got a nice logical volume
(LV) layout like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;start ---------------------------------------- end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;      |    root    |    home    |    swap    |&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;                          ^&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;                     problematic&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thus, my plan is remove the &lt;code&gt;swap&lt;/code&gt; LV, extend the &lt;code&gt;home&lt;/code&gt; LV, somehow gather
all the files' bits into the start of the LV, then shrink the &lt;code&gt;home&lt;/code&gt; back,
and recreate the swap. Okay, here we go! First of all, remove the &lt;code&gt;swap&lt;/code&gt; LV
and extend the &lt;code&gt;home&lt;/code&gt; LV:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;# swapoff /dev/swap&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;# lvremove /dev/swap&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;# lvextend -l +100%FREE /dev/home&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And the layout become like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;start ---------------------------------------- end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;      |    root    |           home          |&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;                                 ^&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;                            problematic&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After that, I use &lt;code&gt;btrfs scrub start /dev/home&lt;/code&gt; to see if everything is
fine. Since I'm not patient, I run &lt;code&gt;watch btrfs scrub status /dev/home&lt;/code&gt; so I
can monitor it. 10 Gigs, 30 Gigs, 50 Gigs, ..., and some minutes later it's
done! Nice, so the files are really goes beyond the end &lt;code&gt;/dev/home&lt;/code&gt; LV and
we can try to gather the files. How do we do that? Fortunately, BTRFS
provides an on-line defragment tool with &lt;code&gt;btrfs filesystem defragment
&amp;lt;partition&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. At this point, I'm not really sure how BTRFS defragment works.
Usually it works like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="defragment illustration" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d0/FragmentationDefragmentation.gif" title="Defragment Illustration"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's usually implementation dependent, but nothing to lose right? (unless
the defragment feature is still experimental and I'll lose all my date
T_T). So I ran &lt;code&gt;btrfs filesystem defragment /dev/home&lt;/code&gt;, and then wait till
it's done. How to check if it DOES worked? I don't know. Let's just try
return the LVs like before and then run BTRFS scrub:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;# lvresize -L &amp;lt;previous /dev/home size&amp;gt; /dev/home&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;# lvcreate -L &amp;lt;previous /dev/swap size&amp;gt; -n swap &amp;lt;group name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;# mkswap /dev/swap&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;# swapon /dev/swap&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;# btrfs scrub start /dev/home&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="code-line"&gt;# watch btrfs scrub status /dev/home&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After a moment, it says all the filesystem is checked and no errors on
systemd-journald and I can write things again. Yay! It does worked afterall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sure is scary when my keyring almost gone, but it's
fun trying to fix the problem (although I don't know if this is truly a fix
or not). With that said, I think I can fix this because I'm lucky that right
after my &lt;code&gt;/dev/home&lt;/code&gt; LV is my swap LV so I can remove it. I wonder what
should I do if it's not a swap LV (like, if the &lt;code&gt;/dev/root&lt;/code&gt; trying to access
&lt;code&gt;/dev/home&lt;/code&gt;)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two things that I learn from this incident:
- Don't straight restart your machine if something failed on your computer.
  Make sure you don't have any loss first before going for the
  restart-route. Besides your own data, save the error logs that you got for
  future diagnose purpose (in case the error is not saved). You can always use
  pen and paper if you can't save it digitally.
- Actually, try not to use the restart-route if possible, especially if you
  use the computer quite often. It's just running from the problem.
  Restart-route will solve transient problems, and most likely it will
  happened again. Of course I can say this because I got the basic idea of
  how it works, but then again, you should have a friend (you do right?)
  that understand what happened. You're not living alone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="btrfs"></category><category term="lvm"></category><category term="filesystem"></category><category term="troubleshooting"></category></entry></feed>